A Guide to the Citizens for a Better City, 1959-2012
Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Citizens for a Better City, 1959-2012
Falls Church History Room, Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Record Group 4-1
11 boxes
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
In 1979 the CBC transferred its file to the Mary Riley Styles Public Library. The original transfer included campaign materials from 1959 to 1976. The resolution also allowed for additional materials to be incorporated into the collection. Additional files were donated by Edward B. Strait. There are no restrictions to access the files.
Biographical/Historical Note
The Citizens for a Better Council, later renamed Citizens for a Better City, was formed in 1959. A group of citizens was concerned that the City Council was ignoring a referendum that was passed to expand the high school. They ran three candidates for City Council, and all three were elected. In the following election years, the CBC would hold a convention to nominate candidates to run for City Council on a non-partisan basis. The CBC no longer holds nominating conventions, but is still active in the community.
Scope and Content
Edward B. Strait, a Falls Church resident, collected and held the files of the CBC. These files were donated to the Mary Riley Styles Public Library in 2013 per his instructions. These were added to the files already held by the library.
The collection of the CBC is arranged into eight series created by the archivist. It covers the time period 1959 to 2012.
Series 1: By-Laws and History
Series 2: Annual Meetings
Series 3: Executive Committee
Series 4: Elections. Each election contains files for the nominating convention and the campaigns of CBC candidates. Campaign materials are also included here. Most election also have a file of newspaper clippings. This series was arranged chronologically.
Series 5: Subject files
Series 6: Falls Church
Series 7: Publications
Series 8: Newspaper Clippings
Series 9: Audiovisual materials and Photographs
Series 10: Edward B. Strait
Series 1, 2, 3, 4, 7, and 8 are arranged chronologically. The files in Series 5 and 6 are in alphabetical order.
Arrangement
The files were reorganized into series by the archivist. The CBC had arranged the files by year for the Executive Committee, the convention records and the campaign materials. Previous to the donation, the Falls Church History Room had some files of the CBC which were incorporated into the Edward Strait donation. Files retained the names given by the CBC. Most files are in chronological order except as noted above. Newspaper clippings pertaining to a particular election are included in Series 4 and were placed in separate folders; other newspaper clippings were placed in Series 8.
Contents List
*File has a photograph/photographs
- Series 1: By-Laws and History (Box 1)
  - By Laws, 1959-2011 (Folder 1)
  - Executive Boards, 1959-2012 (Folder 2)
  - History, 1959-2009 (Folder 3)
- Series 2: Annual Meetings (Box 1)
  - Annual Meetings, 1960-1979 (Folder 1)
  - Annual Meetings, 1980-2011 (Folder 2)
- Series 3: Executive Committee, 1961-2011 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee, 1961 (Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee, 1962 (Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee, 1963 (Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee, 1964 (Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee, 1965 (Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee, 1966 (Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee, 1967 (Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee, 1968 (Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee, 1969 (Folder 9)
  - Executive Committee, 1970 (Folder 10)
- Series 3: Executive Committee, 1961-2011, continued (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee, 1971 (Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee, 1972 (Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee, 1973 (Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee, 1974 (Folder 14)
  - Executive Committee, 1975 (Folder 15)
  - Executive Committee, 1976 (Folder 16)
  - Executive Committee, 1977 (Folder 17)
  - Executive Committee, 1978 (Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee, 1979 (Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee, 1980 (Folder 20)
  - Executive Committee, 1981 (Folder 21)
  - Executive Committee, 1982 (Folder 22)
  - Executive Committee, 1983 (Folder 23)
  - Executive Committee, 1984 (Folder 24)
  - Executive Committee, 1985 (Folder 25)
  - Executive Committee, 1986 (Folder 26)
  - Executive Committee, 1987 (Folder 27)
  - Executive Committee, 1988 (Folder 28)
  - Executive Committee, 1989 (Folder 29)
  - Executive Committee, 1990 (Folder 30)
- Series 3: Executive Committee, 1961-2011, continued (Box 3)
  - Executive Committee, 1991 (Folder 31)
  - Executive Committee, 1992 (Folder 32)
  - Executive Committee, 1993 (Folder 33)
  - Executive Committee, 1994 (Folder 34)
  - Executive Committee, 1995 (Folder 35)
  - Executive Committee, 1996 (Folder 36)
  - Executive Committee, 1997 (Folder 37)
  - Executive Committee, 1998 (Folder 38)
  - Executive Committee, 1999 (Folder 39)
  - Executive Committee, 2000 (Folder 40)
  - Executive Committee, 2001 (Folder 41)
  - Executive Committee, 2002 (Folder 42)
  - Executive Committee, 2003 (Folder 43)
  - Executive Committee, 2004 (Folder 44)
  - Executive Committee, 2005 (Folder 45)
  - Executive Committee, 2006 (Folder 46)
  - Executive Committee, 2007 (Folder 47)
  - Executive Committee, 2008 (Folder 48)
  - Executive Committee, 2009 (Folder 49)
  - Executive Committee, 2010 (Folder 50)
  - Executive Committee, 2011 (Folder 51)
- Series 4: Elections, 1959-2012 (Box 3)
  - 1959 Campaign Issues (Folder 1)
  - 1959 Election (Folder 2)
  - 1959 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 3)
  - 1960 Election – Public Works Improvement Bond Issue (Folder 4)
- Series 4: Elections, 1959-2012, continued (Box 4)
  - 1961 Nominating Convention, March 9, 1961 (Folder 5)
  - 1961 Election* (Folder 6)
  - 1961 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 7)
  - 1961 Election - Newspaper Clippings from Ed Strait (Folder 8)
  - 1963 Nominating Convention, March 6, 1963 (Folder 9)
  - 1963 Election (Folder 10)
  - 1963 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 11)
  - 1965 Nominating Convention, March 11, 1965 (Folder 12)
  - 1965 Election (Folder 13)
  - 1965 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 14)
  - 1967 Nominating Convention, March 16, 1967 (Folder 15)
  - 1967 Election (Folder 16)
  - 1967 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 17)
  - 1969 Nominating Convention, March 6, 1969 (Folder 18)
  - 1969 Election (Folder 19)
  - 1969 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 20)
  - 1971 Nominating Convention, February 4, 1971 (Folder 21)
  - 1971 Election (Folder 22)
  - 1971 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 23)
  - 1971 Election - Newspaper Clippings from Ed Strait (Folder 24)
- Series 4: Elections, 1959-2012, continued (Box 5)
  - 1974 Nominating Convention, February 5, 1974 (Folder 25)
  - 1974 Election (Folder 26)
  - 1974 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 27)
  - 1976 Nominating Convention, February 4, 1976 (Folder 28)
  - 1976 Election (Folder 29)
  - 1978 Nominating Convention, February 1, 1978 (Folder 30)
  - 1978 Election (Folder 31)
  - 1980 Nominating Convention, February 12, 1980 (Folder 32)
  - 1980 Election (Folder 33)
  - 1982 Election - Candidate Selection Committee (Folder 34)
  - 1982 Nominating Convention, February 3, 1982 (Folder 35)
  - 1982 Election (Folder 36)
  - 1984 Nominating Convention, February 14, 1984 (Folder 37)
  - 1984 Election (Folder 38)
  - 1984 Election - Finance Committee (Folder 39)
  - 1986 Nominating Convention, February 12, 1986 (Folder 40)
  - 1986 Election (Folder 41)
  - 1986 Election - Finance Committee (Folder 42)
  - 1988 Nominating Convention, February 4, 1988 (Folder 43)
  - 1988 Election (Folder 44)
  - 1988 Election - Finance Committee (Folder 45)
  - 1988 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 46)
  - 1990 Nominating Convention, February 14, 1990 (Folder 47)
  - 1990 Election (Folder 48)
  - 1990 Election - Campaign Finances (Folder 49)
  - 1990 Election - Campaign Guest Book (Folder 50)
- Series 4: Elections, 1959-2012, continued (Box 6)
  - 1990 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 51)
  - 1992 Nominating Convention, January 15, 1992 (Folder 52)
  - 1992 Election (Folder 53)
  - 1992 Election - Issue Papers (Folder 54)
  - 1992 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 55)
  - 1992 Election - Ward Operations Notebook (Folder 56)
  - 1993 School Board Election (Folder 57)
  - 1994 Nominating Convention, February 9, 1994 (Folder 58)
  - 1994 Election (folder 1 of 2) (Folder 59)
  - 1994 Election (folder 2 of 2) (Folder 60)
  - 1994 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 61)
  - 1994 School Board Nominating Convention, February 16, 1994 (Folder 62)
  - 1996 Nominating Convention, January 31, 1996 (Folder 63)
  - 1996 Election (folder 1 of 2) (Folder 64)
  - 1996 Election (folder 2 of 2) (Folder 65)
- Series 4: Elections, 1959-2012, continued (Box 7)
  - 1996 School Board Nominating Convention, January 23, 1996 (Folder 66)
  - 1997 Election for Sheriff (Folder 67)
  - 1998 Nominating Convention, February 17, 1998 (Folder 68)
  - 1998 Election (folder 1 of 2) (Folder 69)
  - 1998 Election (folder 2 of 2) (Folder 70)
  - 1998 Community Center Referendum (Folder 71)
  - 1998 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 72)
  - 1999 Referendum, Cherry Hill Park - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 73)
  - 2000 Nominating Convention, February 12, 2000 (Folder 74)
  - 2000 Election (Folder 75)
  - 2000 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 76)
  - 2002 Nominating Convention, February 23, 2002 (Folder 77)
  - 2002 Election (Folder 78)
  - 2002 Election -Newspaper Clippings (Folder 79)
  - 2004 Nominating Convention, February 14, 2004 (Folder 80)
- Series 4: Elections, 1959-2012, continued (Box 8)
  - 2004 Election (folder 1 of 2) (Folder 81)
  - 2004 Election (folder 2 of 2) (Folder 82)
  - 2004 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 83)
  - 2006 Nominating Convention, February 11, 2006 (Folder 84)
  - 2006 Election (Folder 85)
  - 2006 Election - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 86)
  - 2008 Nominating Convention, February 23, 2008 (Folder 87)
  - 2008 Election (Folder 88)
  - 2010 Nominating Convention, February 20, 2010 (Folder 89)
  - 2010 Election (Folder 90)
  - 2012 Election (Folder 91)
  - CBC Candidates, 1959-2010 (Folder 92)
  - Elections, 1972-1989 (Folder 93)
  - Nominating Convention Programs, 1961-1988 (Folder 94)
  - Nominating Convention Programs, 1990-2010 (Folder 95)
  - Ward Captain's Manual. [n.d.] (Folder 96)
- Series 5: Subject Files (Box 8)
  - Anniversaries – Founding CBC, 1959-1999 (Folder 1)
  - Byrd Machine, Newspaper Clippings, 1957 (Folder 2)
  - Committee on Principles, 1968 (Folder 3)
  - Dinners and Dining, 1964, 1966, 1983, 2010 (Folder 4)
  - Forums, 1971-2004 (Folder 5)
  - Future Directions, 1984-1988 (Folder 6)
- Series 5: Subject Files, continued (Box 9)
  - Good Government Survey, [1969-1970?] (Folder 7)
  - Governors and Senators of Virginia, 1917-1966 (Folder 8)
  - Hatch Act (Folder 9)
  - Issues Subcommittee, 1972 (Folder 10)
  - Jane and Wayne Dexter Award, 2001-2009 (Folder 11)
  - Loyalty Oath, 1960 (Folder 12)
  - Mailing List, 2004 (Folder 13)
  - Membership lists, 1967-2011 (with gaps) (Folder 14)
  - Policies, 1968 (Folder 15)
  - Positions, 1972 (Folder 16)
  - Principles, [n.d.] (Folder 17)
  - Songs, 1979, 1983 (Folder 18)
  - Time Capsule, 1976 (Folder 19)
  - Transfer Agreement with the Mary Riley Styles Public Library, 1979 (Folder 20)
  - Website, 2000 (Folder 21)
- Series 6: Falls Church, (Box 9)
  - All America Cities Award Competition, 1980 (Folder 1)
  - All American City, Fairfax County Sun Echo, March 29, 1962 (Folder 2)
  - Apartment Houses in Falls Church [n.d.] (Folder 3)
  - Blur, October-December 1987 (Published by the Citizens for Better Government) (Folder 4)
  - Broad Street Referendum, 1989 (Folder 5)
  - Central Business District, 1968 (Folder 6)
  - Citizens for Modern Financial Management, 1984-1986 (folder 1 of 2) (Folder 7)
  - Citizens for Modern Financial Management, 1984-1986 (folder 2 of 2) (Folder 8)
  - City Charter – Proposed Changes, 1969-1970 (Folder 9)
  - City Council Election, 1955 (Folder 10)
  - City Council Election, 1957 (Folder 11)
  - City Council, Goals and Objectives, 1975-1977 (Folder 12)
  - City Council Meetings, 1957-1960 [incomplete] (Folder 13)
  - City Council Members, 1948-2008 (Folder 14)
  - City Council Report, 1959-1960 (Folder 15)
  - Commercial Establishments Built in the City, September 1, 1959-August 31, 1960 (Folder 16)
  - Commissioner of Revenue Election, 1957 (Folder 17)
  - Elected Mayors, 1875-1964 (Folder 18)
  - Falls Church Assessments, 1989-1990 (Folder 19)
- Series 6: Falls Church, continued (Box 10)
  - Falls Church Citizens for Progress, 1971 (Folder 20)
  - Falls Church Citizens Organization (FCC0), 1988-1995 (Folder 21)
  - Falls Church Coalition for Smart Growth, 2002 (Folder 22)
  - Falls Church Taxpayers League, 1961 (Folder 23)
  - First Virginia Bankshares, 1967-1969 (Folder 24)
  - George Mason Bond Coalition, Solicitation of Funds, 1991 (Folder 25)
  - League of Women Voters of Falls Church, 1965, 2003 (Folder 26)
  - Plain Talk, 1970-1971, 1989 (Folder 27)
  - Planned Unit Development, 1970 (Folder 28)
  - Planned Unit Development, Resolution, 1974 (Folder 29)
  - Registered Voters, 1992 (Folder 30)
  - Registered Voters, 1994 (Folder 31)
  - Registered Voters, 1992-1995, 2001-2002 (total numbers) (Folder 32)
  - School Board, 1958-1968 (Folder 33)
  - Village Preservation and Improvement Society, Revitalization of the Four Mile Run Urban Forest Stream Valley meeting, March 18, 1992 (Folder 34)
- Series 7: Publications (Box 10)
  - CBC Notes, 1967-1989 (Folder 1)
  - CBC Notes, 1990-2004 (Folder 2)
  - CBC Beacon, 2001-2009 (Folder 3)
- Series 8: Newspaper Clippings (Box 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1959, 1961, 1963-1964 (Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1965-1966 (Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1967-1968 (Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1969-1971 (Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1976, 1979-1980 (Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1988-1991, 1994 (Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 2001 (Folder 7)
- Series 9: Audio-visual (Box 10)
  - Photographs (Folder 1)
  - VHS Cassette, CBC Campaign, 1990, "The Candidates, the Issues" (Item 1)
  - CD, CBC Convention, 2004 (Item 2)
  - Floppy disc, By Laws, 1994 (Item 3)
  - Floppy disc, CBC Convention, 1996 (Item 4)
  - Floppy disc, CBC Convention, 1998 (excel files) (Item 5)
  - Floppy disc, CBC Convention, 2000 (Item 6)
  - Floppy disc, CBC Convention, 2004 (Item 7)
- Series 10: Edward B. Strait (Box 11)
  - Campaign, 1969 (Folder 1)
  - President of CBC, 1989-1990 (Folder 2)
  - Emails, 1998 (Folder 3)
  - Emails, January-March 2000 (Folder 4)
  - Emails, March-May 2000 (Folder 5)